Cotton Land Company records, 1909-1970
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Cotton Land Company records, 1909-1970
MS 306
Cotton Land Company
Contains official records of the Cotton Land Company, and the Cotton Water and Irrigation Company, 1909-1970, relating to land development and water rights to company lands located in Mohave County, Arizona, on the east side of the Colorado River. Includes articles of incorporation, minutes, stockbooks, correspon-dence, maps, legal and financial documents, and photographs documenting the activities of the companies, especially in the periods between 1910-1930 and 1945-1965.
5.8 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Historical Note
The Cotton Land Company was incorporated on December 20, 1909 in Arizona Territory for a term of 25 years; no application for renewal was made. Its place of business was Cottonia, Mohave County. The nature of the charter of the land company was to purchase and acquire lands to own, manage, improve, subdivide, sell and dispose, as well as any subsidiary business needed to achieve those ends. Signers of the incorporation papers were W.I. Hollings-worth, W.J. Hole, D.M. Martin, Louis Evans, and W.J. Burton. During its lengthy liquidation, its place of business was listed through offices in Los Angeles.
The 1914 overflow of the Colorado River destroyed the levee system which had been under construction by the company at that time, thus halting the develop-ment plans for the lands. From 1915 until 1939 the land was either rented to private individuals for farming or used by the company for cattle raising. Thereafter, the company held the lands pending the probate of certain estates, and then distributed the holdings to the stockholders.
The Cotton Water and Irrigation Company was incorporated in 1909 and was assigned water rights to the acquisitions of the land company.
Organization
The files were received somewhat disorganized in 1981. An attempt was made to reconstruct the original order where possible. It should be noted that many of the file headings reflected individual names while others were labeled as to the location or use of the land involved, but both folders related to the same lawsuit, rental, or leasing agreement. When possible, related file folders are filed next to each other. Not all folder titles are listed for the Numbered Files in the preliminary inventory below.
This collection is organized into two series:
I. General Files, 1909-1970
II. Numbered Files, No Date
Scope and Content Note
Contains official records of the Cotton Land Company, and the Cotton Water and Irrigation Company, 1909-1970, relating to land development and water rights to company lands located in Mohave County, Arizona, on the east side of the Colorado River. Includes articles of incorporation, minutes, stockbooks, correspon-dence, maps, legal and financial documents, and photographs documenting the activities of the companies, especially in the periods between 1910-1930 and 1945-1965.
The bulk of documents in this collection relate to the history and activities of the Cotton Land Company, especially in regard to the leasing of lands, and litigation on various estate and contractual matters. The General files contain the official records of the two companies, as well as topical files relating to everyday business and the final distribution of assets. The leases and subleases in the files are with individuals, partnerships, and corporations located in Arizona and California, and doing business as Schweitzer Company, Bermuda Planta-tions, Mohave Valley Farms, Mohave Venture Farms, D.W. Hulet, John R. Mahoney, McKellips and Gregg, Hubert Merryweat-her, River Farms, and Sherrill and LaFolle-tte.
The Litigation files involve claims between the company and the United States of America, John R. Mahoney, Hubert Merryweather, Bermurda Plantations, and others. The files consist of correspon-dence and legal papers relating to the issues and their resolution. The largest case involves the company's claim against the govern-ment for the loss of about 9,000 acres of land due to the construc-tion of the Parker Dam. The company's witness, Charles H. Lee, an engineer, prepared several reports on the causes of flooding in Mohave County. Related documents are found in the Maps and Charts files and in the General files.
The Indians files include correspondence about leases and exchanges of lands with the Colorado River and Mohave Indians during the 1930s and 1940s. Correspondents include governmental personnel in the Office of Indian Affairs, Congress, representatives of the Indians, surveyors, appraisers, and other interested parties.
Of interest in the Maps and Charts files are several folders including: a 1940 report by C.H. Purcell on "Hydraulic reconnais-sance for proposed crossing of Colorado River and bottoms near Needles;" possible acquisition of certain lands by Metropolitan Water District of Southern Califor-nia; Charles Lee supplemental report on flooding of lands in Mohave Valley, including discharge records of the Colorado River; and additional reports, some by M.M. Kaufman, on surveys of company lands, and on lands taken by the government.
The Taxes files contain various correspondence and forms for corporate income reporting, while the Title files contain abstract of title to land patents, deeds, and accretions involving proper-ties of the company and the Santa Fe Pacific Railroad Company. The Water Rights files include a report by C.P. Vetter on the effects of the constant rise of the Colorado River bed in the vicinity of Needles, and documents relating to the acquisition, leasing, and ownership of Colorado River water by the company.
Cotton Land Company; Cotton Water and Irrigation Company; Mohave Venture Farms; Bermuda Plantations; River Farms; Water rights -- Colorado River (Colo.-Mexico); Business enterprises -- Arizona -- Archives; Business enterprises -- California -- Archives; Real estate development -- Arizona -- Mohave County; Floods -- Colorado River (Colo.-Mexico); Colorado River Indian Reservation (Ariz. and Calif.); Colorado River (Colo.-Mexico) -- Water rights; Parker Dam (Ariz. and Calif.); Arizona -- Mohave County -- Land development; Fort Mohave Indian Reservation (Ariz. and Calif.); Mohave County (Ariz.) -- History; Correspondence; Photographs; Articles of Incorporation; Minutes
Separated Material
Approximately 1.5 feet of duplicates and check vouchers were separated from the collection.
Container List
- Series I: General Files, 1909-1970
  - Cotton Water and Irrigation Company
    - Articles of Incorporation and Bylaws. 1909-1925 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Minutes. 1910-1933 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Stock Journal and Ledger. 1910-1933 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Cotton Land Company
    - Articles of Incorporation and Bylaws. 1909-1925 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Minutes. 1910-1968 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Stockbook. 1910-1957 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Stock Journal and Ledger. 1910-1933 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Accounting. 1955-1960 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Agents, escrows, etc. 1955-1958 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Balance Sheets. 1934, 1940-1960 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Bermuda Plantations. 1952-1959 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Documents. 1909-1970 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Gas station sale. 1955 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Hollingsworth Corporation. 1955 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Journals. 1924-1970 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Lawyer: L. B. Binford. 1954-1964 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Legal fees. 1956-1961 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Liquidation. 1956-1959 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - D. W. Hulet. 1955-1960 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - D. W. Hulet (continued). 1955-1960 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - McKellips and Gregg. 1955-1966 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Merriweather and Mahoney Suits. 1952-1958 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Mohave Valley Farms. 1951-1959 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - River Farms. 1958-1966 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Sherrill and LaFollette. 1955-1970 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Jerry Skousen: Arizona subdivisions trust. 1955-1965 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Sundt Construction. 1958 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - D. H. Swan matters. 1952-1962 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Series II: Numbered Files, No Date
  - Current Lease Options (100). No Date (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Litigation (200). No Date (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Improvement of Land (300). No Date (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Indians (400). No Date (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Maps and Charts (500). No Date (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Maps and Charts (continued). No Date (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous (600). No Date (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Past Sales Negotiations (700). No Date (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Sales to Government (800). No Date (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Taxes (900). No Date (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Title (1000). No Date (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Water Rights (1100). No Date (Box 6, Folder 7)